Arabella Huntington Papers
Arabella Huntington Papers
1888-1925
Huntington, Arabella Duval, 1850 or 51-1924.
1.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American philanthropist and collector. Her first husband was financier Collis P. Huntington; her second husband, Henry E. Huntington. Correspondence (1892-1923); inventories of paintings, jewelry, and real estate; bills and receipts from art dealers, galleries and stores, including Joseph Duveen, J. Seligmann, and Tiffany & Co.
149066
Biographical History
Arabella Duval Huntington was born in Richmond, Virginia, in 1851. Her parents, Mr. and Mrs. R.M. Yarrington, raised Arabella in Virginia where she remained until her marriage at the age of eighteen. She married a Mr. Worsham of New York City in 1869 and returned there with him. However, he died a year later, leaving Arabella with an infant son, Archer Milton.* The next fourteen years were spent raising her son and educating him herself. In 1884, she married Collis P. Huntington, railroad builder and financier. Mr. Huntington legally adopted Archer. They lived a very happy life together until his death in 1900.
For the next ten years, Mrs. Huntington tried to carry on her husband's interests, visiting his shipyards and supporting charities in his name. In 1913, she remarried once more. Mutual interests in art attracted her to Collis P. Huntington's nephew, Henry E. Huntington, and after their marriage they traveled extensively in Europe, gathering the materials for what was to be the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery in California. She divided her time between New York and her husband's home in California. She remained active in numerous charities and good works until her death in 1924.
*This history has been questioned. A. Hyatt Mayor, Arabella's nephew, has suggested that Archer Milton was in fact the illegitimate son of Collis Huntington. [RR]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers of Arabella Huntington contain correspondence, subject files, bills and receipts, and manuscripts.
Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, and correspondence to and from others. The incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author. The outgoing correspondence if filed chronologically. (Dates: 1892, 1901-1902, 1905-1919, 1922-1923.)
Subject files contains accounts, blueprints, inventories, legal papers, material pertaining to the Roadside Mine, and related items. These materials are arranged alphabetically by type or subject. (Dates: 1891, 1897, 1909, 1912, 1920, 1923-1925.)
Bills and receipts consists of bills or receipts sent to Mrs. Huntington by various firms, merchants, charities, etc. These are arranged alphabetically by name of the firm or individual. (Dates: 1888-1889, 1902-1925)
Manuscripts includes three articles by others, all typescript. These are undated.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into incoming and outgoing; within this it is arranged alphabetically. The other three series are arranged alphabetically by subject, name, and title respectively.
Related Material
See also the following:
Anna Hyatt Huntington Papers
Archer Milton Huntington Papers
Collis P. Huntington Papers
Huntington Estate Records
Subject and Genre Headings
Duveen, Joseph Duveen, Baron, 1869-1939.; Huntington, Arabella Duval, 1850 or 51-1924.; Seligmann, Jacques, 1858-1923.; Tiffany and Company.; Art -- Collectors and collecting -- United States.; Art -- Private collections.; Art dealers.; Women philanthropists -- United States.; Upper class -- United States; Bills of sale.; Correspondence.; Inventories.; Receipts (financial records); Collectors.; Philanthropists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence
    - A, B, D (Box 1)
    - Duveen, Joseph, 1907-1909; 1913,; 1916,; 1923 (Box 1)
    - F-G, I-K, M, V, unidentified (Box 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence
    - 1901-02, 1905 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to and from others (Box 1)
- Subject file
  - Accounts (Box 1)
  - Blueprints
    - Throggs Neck, New York (Box 1)
    - Kanawaha Co., W. Va. and New York City (Throggs Neck) (Box 1)
  - Exhibition catalogue, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Inventories
    - "Additions to Inventory of Things at Beauregard", 1920 (Box 1)
    - Furnishings, 1897; 1912,; 1920,; 1923,; undated (Box 1)
    - Jewelry (Box 1)
    - Paintings (Box 1)
    - Real estate (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1897 (Box 1)
  - Roadside Mine, 1923-1925; correspondence, blueprint, photographs; 3 folders (Box 1)
- Bills and receipts
  - A (Box 2)
  - Anderson Galleries, 1916; 1920,; 1922-24 (Box 2)
  - B (Box 2)
  - Baumgarten & Company, 1917; 1919-22 (Box 2)
  - Black, Starr, & Frost, 1906; 1924 (Box 2)
  - Blakeslee, T.J., 1910-1913 (Box 2)
  - Brandeis, Edward, 1911 (Box 2)
  - C (Box 2)
  - Camerino, J.G., 1903; 1907-1909,; 1912-1915,; 1921 (Box 2)
  - Cartier, 1907-1914; 1918,; 1921,; 1923 (Box 2)
  - Cattadori, Pietro, 1922-1923; undated (Box 2)
  - Clark, Thomas B., 1919-1920; 1922-1923 (Box 2)
  - Crichton Brothers, 1912; 1914,; 1916,; 1920 (Box 2)
  - D (Box 2)
  - Duveen, Joseph, 1906-1908; 1910,; 1911-21,; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - E (Box 2)
  - Ehrich Galleries, 1906-1907; 1909,; 1911-1913,; 1919,; 1923,; undated (Box 2)
  - F (Box 2)
  - Fischer Art Galleries, 1911-1912; undated (Box 2)
  - Fischhof, Eugene, 1898-1899 (Box 2)
  - French, P.W. & Co., 1909-1923 (Box 2)
  - G (Box 2)
  - Gould, Raymond C., 1918; 1922-1924 (Box 2)
  - Gump, S.&G., Co., 1922-1924 (Box 2)
  - H (Box 3)
  - Harper, Donald, 1915; 1921 (Box 3)
  - J (Box 3)
  - K (Box 3)
  - Langweil, Madame F., 1910-1911 (Box 3)
  - "The Little Shop", 1902-1907 (Box 3)
  - Los Angeles Museum, 1923 (Box 3)
  - M (Box 3)
  - Marsh, G.F. & Co., 1920-1923 (Box 3)
  - McCarthy, A.E., 1917; 1921,; 1923 (Box 3)
  - McGough, P.J., 1920; 1923-24 (Box 3)
  - N (Box 3)
  - O (Box 3)
  - P (Box 3)
  - Partridge, Frank, 1910-1911; 1913-1915,; 1920,; undated (Box 3)
  - R (Box 3)
  - Rosenbach Co., 1924 (Box 3)
  - S (Box 3)
  - Schaus, Wm., 1907 (Box 3)
  - Seligmann, J., 1907-1916; 1918-1920,; 1922-1923; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Smith, H.H., 1912 (Box 3)
  - Tiffany & Co., 1902; 1904,; 1910-1912,; 1919 (Box 3)
  - Tiffany Studios, 1907; 1919-1920 (Box 3)
  - V (Box 3)
  - W (Box 3)
  - Wunderlich & Co., 1906-1909; undated (Box 3)
  - Y (Box 3)
  - Unidentified (Box 3)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles by others (Box 3)